Hey everyone, it's me.
Welcome to another skill building section for reading,
and we're going into the unknown realm today.
First of all, I have a question for you.
Have you ever thought that you would try
your best to practice reading?
However, you see many new words when reading
and have to constantly look for their meanings,
which is really time consuming.
It can take you an hour to read
a few sentences.
Another thing is that when studying at home,
you can use a dictionary to look up new words.
But when taking the actual IELTS exam,
what should you do?
Should you just give up?
Understanding this feeling.
Today, I'm going to introduce to you a
skill called understanding vocabulary in context,
which helps reduce the use of dictionaries to look up new words.
Another term for this is guessing meaning.
First of all, we're going to discuss some advantages of
understanding vocabulary in context or guessing meaning.
Increase reading efficiency.
Guessing the meanings of words helps us to
not depend on dictionaries too much,
allowing us to deal with text, even in situations where
dictionaries are not available, such as in the exam room.
Moreover, it will speed up the process of
handling text and enhance reading comprehension a lot.
From that, you can form good reading habits
and feel less stressed when having to look up many new words.
Reduce the number of words to learn.
You probably heard that to achieve a 6.5 in IELTS,
you need to learn thousands of English words.
This number can make you want to give up.
However, with the skill of guessing meaning,
the number of words to learn can significantly decrease.
It may even come down to just hundreds
of the most important ones.
Based on them, you can guess the meanings
of the majority of unknown words.
Now, I'm going to give you three steps
for guessing the meaning of an unknown word
while reading.
Step 1.
Decide whether it is necessary to guess the
meaning of an unknown word or not.
Step 2.
Read the information area that contains the unknown
word carefully and find clues about its meaning.
Step 3.
Guess its meaning to some extent based on the clues.
Let's analyse each step in detail.
Step 1.
Decide whether it is necessary to guess the
meaning of an unknown word or not.
Perhaps this sounds strange, because you may think
that you have to guess the meaning of
every word or understand all of them.
It's not always like that.
Sometimes we can completely skip some words, but
still understand the information being conveyed.
In that case, guessing the meaning of an
unknown word might not be really useful or
not help us answer reading questions faster.
Therefore, the first thing we need to do
is to decide whether it is necessary to
guess the meaning of an unknown word or not.
We can do this by skipping that word
and continuing to read.
If we still understand what the sentence conveys,
then we can completely ignore it.
If we keep reading and don't understand anything,
then we need to go back to that word
and guess its meaning to some extent.
Let's take two sentences below as an example.
In these two sentences, I guess that
there are two unfamiliar words to many of you.
Among them, this word is the one we
can skip guessing its meaning and still understand
what the sentence talks about.
Because there is a noun there, the commitment
is a noun, meaning a promise or firm decision to do something.
So, it's okay if you don't know what this word means.
However, you need to know the word dissipate.
What meaning drop out after just one month?
If we don't understand this word,
the meaning of the whole sentence may be unclear and
we will miss an event or cause of the action drop out.
So, between the two new words, we should
focus more on guessing the meaning of dissipate.
At this point, you still haven't learned about
the clue to guess the meaning.
I'm going to tell you what these two words mean.
If you pay a little more attention, you
can save a large amount of time and
effort in reading comprehension.
Let's continue with step two.
Read the information area that contains the unknown
word carefully and find clues about its meaning.
For reading the information area that contains the unknown word,
you should follow this order.
Read the sentence that contains the unknown word carefully.
In many cases, only one sentence can provide
us with enough clues to understand the meaning of a word.
This sentence is also what we should focus
on the most to understand the message being conveyed.
If the sentence that contains the unknown word
doesn't provide enough context for us to guess its meaning,
we should read the sentences before and after it.
These three sentences will form an information area
of the unknown word, and it's likely that
the clues about its meaning are located in this area.
After reading carefully, we will find clues about its meaning.
We're going to talk about this in the
following part of the lesson.
Normally, there are four types of clues.
Number one, grammar and word form clues.
Number two, definition clues.
Number three, linking word clues.
And number four, context clues.
All right, now we only have step three,
guess its meaning to some extent based on the clues.
This step is quite clear.
We will guess the meaning of the unknown word
based on the clues.
However, the meaning may be true to some extent,
which is enough for us to understand
the general information being conveyed.
Now, you may wonder, what if there are
no clues for its meaning, or I still
can't guess it even using the clues?
Of course, this situation can happen, and I
will divide it into two possibilities.
When you practice at home.
At this time, you can use some tools like dictionaries.
So, if you have tried your best but
couldn't guess the meaning of a word, you
can use some English-English dictionaries such as
Cambridge or Oxford to look it up.
At the intermediate level, I highly recommend using
an English-English dictionary to understand
the correct meaning of a word and read examples to
understand how it's used in a sentence.
When you take the actual IELTS exam.
Now you don't have any tools to support you,
so my only advice is to make your best guess.
You have to guess the meaning of an unfamiliar word,
even if it's unclear.
If you can't do anything with it, ignore it and move on.
However, with what you will learn in this course,
I'm quite sure that you will be able to
guess the meanings of words enough
to get a band 6 or higher in IELTS reading.
We have just discussed the steps for guessing meaning.
In the next part, we're going to take
a deep dive into four types of clues
about guessing meaning.
So, let's move on.
Let's discover the first type.
Grammar and word form clues.
Guessing meaning based on grammar and word form.
The knowledge of grammar and word form in
English is an important tool to help us
guess the meanings of unknown words.
About grammar, let's take a look at some common cases.
Active voice, passive voice.
This can help us know whether the subject of a sentence
is the one performing the action
or the one being affected by the action.
For example.
Linguists study the intricacies of language,
analyzing its structure, evolution, and cultural significance
Here we have the word "linguists", which sounds strange
to some of you.
However, we can identify that this is an active sentence.
So, linguists is the subject performing the action.
And the action here is to study.
From this, we can see that this unfamiliar
word must be a noun referring to a
person who can do the action study.
That's for now.
To be more specific about what linguists mean,
we need other clues.
We will get back to this sentence later.
I have another example.
The premises for quality education are ensured by
implementing rigorous curriculum standards
and employing highly qualified teachers.
The word "premises" is also new to you, am I right?
We can see that this sentence is the
passive voice with are ensured.
So, the subject here is being affected by
the verb ensure, meaning to make sure that
something happens or is definite.
So, it must be something related to quality education,
which is ensured in some ways.
The next grammar clue is relative clause.
When a noun is followed by a relative clause,
the clause will modify it.
And we just need to look at the
relative pronoun or relative adverb to guess what
the noun refers to.
If it's who or whom, it's about a person.
If it's which, it indicates an object.
If it's where, it mentions a place.
And if it's when, it shows a time.
For example, the subsidy which is provided by
the government for state schools this year aims
to enhance educational opportunities
and support students' learning outcomes.
The word subsidy is unfamiliar to us, but
we can see that it is a noun
referring to an object or an event because
there is a relative clause starting with "which"
right next to it.
Usually, these grammar clues will help us identify
the subject or object in a general way.
Combined with other clues below, we can understand
the meaning more correctly.
So, please stay tuned for the next part.
Regarding word form, this clue is clearer.
We can identify the word form of the
unknown word based on its structure and identify
new words based on our knowledge about root words.
For example, cognitive skills are developed through various
educational and experiential activities.
We can immediately guess that this is an
adjective because it comes before the noun activities
and it has the suffix "-ile", which is
a typical adjective suffix.
When pronouncing this word, does it sound familiar to you?
That's right, experiential.
It is the adjective form of experience, which
is a noun meaning knowledge or skill from
doing, seeing or feeling things.
Therefore, we can see that this word means
based on experience.
There will always be words looking both familiar
and unfamiliar to us like this one when you read a passage.
In those cases, try to identify their word form
and see if they have any common root words.
Sometimes, the definition of a word
we don't know appears in the reading passage.
For example, entrepreneurship, the study of how to
start a new business, has been included in
the curriculum of many universities in recent years.
This word looks unfamiliar and is kind of
English-French, am I right?
However, its definition is right next to it,
the study of how to start a new business.
With this definition, we already understand what to study.
This clue doesn't always appear in the reading passage,
but if it does, it usually goes with some signal words as follows.
The information comes after verbs such as to
be, involve, entail and revolve around.
Meteorology involves the study of atmospheric conditions, weather
patterns and the impact of various factors on our climate.
Nouns ending in "-ogy", often refer to subjects
or fields of study and after the word involved is its definition.
The study of atmospheric conditions, weather patterns and
the impact of various factors on our climate
or the study of weather.
How do you feel about the first two
types of clues about guessing meaning?
Quite helpful, right?
We still have two more, but let's take
a break and recharge your energy before we continue.
See you!